A rectangular matrix is ​​given a [0....n-1, 0....m-1], and requests are made to find the sum (or minimum / maximum) on some sub-rectangles a [x_1....x_2, y_1....y_2], as well as requests for modification of individual matrix elements (ie, type requests a[x][y] = p).

So, we will construct a two-dimensional tree of segments: first the tree of segments along the first coordinate (x), then the second (y).

To make the construction process more understandable, you can forget for a while that the original array was two-dimensional, and leave only the first coordinate. We will construct an ordinary one-dimensional tree of segments, working only with the first coordinate. But as the value of each segment we will write not some number, as in the one-dimensional case, but an entire tree of segments: i.e. at this moment we remember that we also have a second coordinate; but because at this moment it is already fixed that the first coordinate is some segment [l....r], then we actually work with such a strip a [l....r, 0....m-1], and for it we build a tree of segments.

Here is the implementation of the construction of a two-dimensional tree. It actually represents two separate blocks: the construction of a tree of segments along the coordinate x(build_x) and the coordinate y(build_y). If the first function is almost no different from the usual one-dimensional tree, the second one must be dealt with separately with two cases: when the current segment of the first coordinate ([tlx....trx]) has a unit length, and when is a length greater than one. In the first case, we just take the desired value from the matrix a[][], and in the second - we combine the values ​​of two tree segments from the left son and right son in coordinate x.


// Code...
void build_y (int vx, int lx, int rx, int vy, int ly, int ry) {
	if (ly == ry)
		if (lx == rx)
			t[vx][vy] = a[lx][ly];
		else
			t[vx][vy] = t[vx*2][vy] + t[vx*2+1][vy];
	else {
		int my = (ly + ry) / 2;
		build_y (vx, lx, rx, vy*2, ly, my);
		build_y (vx, lx, rx, vy*2+1, my+1, ry);
		t[vx][vy] = t[vx][vy*2] + t[vx][vy*2+1];
	}
}
 
void build_x (int vx, int lx, int rx) {
	if (lx != rx) {
		int mx = (lx + rx) / 2;
		build_x (vx*2, lx, mx);
		build_x (vx*2+1, mx+1, rx);
	}
	build_y (vx, lx, rx, 1, 0, m-1);
}
// Code...


Such a tree of segments occupies, as before, a linear amount of memory, but with a larger constant: (16 * n * m) memory cells. It is clear that it is constructed by the procedure described above, build_x also in linear time.

Now we turn to the processing of requests . We will respond to the two-dimensional query by the same principle: first to break the query on the first coordinate, and then, when we reached some vertex of the tree of segments with the first coordinate, we call the corresponding tree of segments on the second coordinate.


// Code...
int sum_y (int vx, int vy, int tly, int try_, int ly, int ry) {
	if (ly > ry)
		return 0;
	if (ly == tly && try_ == ry)
		return t[vx][vy];
	int tmy = (tly + try_) / 2;
	return sum_y (vx, vy*2, tly, tmy, ly, min(ry,tmy))
		+ sum_y (vx, vy*2+1, tmy+1, try_, max(ly,tmy+1), ry);
}
 
int sum_x (int vx, int tlx, int trx, int lx, int rx, int ly, int ry) {
	if (lx > rx)
		return 0;
	if (lx == tlx && trx == rx)
		return sum_y (vx, 1, 0, m-1, ly, ry);
	int tmx = (tlx + trx) / 2;
	return sum_x (vx*2, tlx, tmx, lx, min(rx,tmx), ly, ry)
		+ sum_x (vx*2+1, tmx+1, trx, max(lx,tmx+1), rx, ly, ry);
}
// Code...


This function works in time O (logn * logm), because it first descends the tree in the first coordinate, and for each traversed vertex of that tree, it makes a query from the usual tree of segments along the second coordinate.

Finally, consider the modification request . We want to learn how to modify the tree of segments in accordance with the change in the value of an element a [x] [y] = p. It is clear that the changes will occur only in those vertices of the first tree of segments that cover the coordinate x(and there will be such O (log n)), and for the trees of the segments corresponding to them, the changes will occur only in those vertices that cover the coordinate y(and there will be such O (log m)). Therefore, the implementation of the modification request will not be very different from the one-dimensional case, only now we first descend the first coordinate, and then - the second.


// Code...
void update_y (int vx, int lx, int rx, int vy, int ly, int ry, int x, int y, int new_val) {
	if (ly == ry) {
		if (lx == rx)
			t[vx][vy] = new_val;
		else
			t[vx][vy] = t[vx*2][vy] + t[vx*2+1][vy];
	}
	else {
		int my = (ly + ry) / 2;
		if (y <= my)
			update_y (vx, lx, rx, vy*2, ly, my, x, y, new_val);
		else
			update_y (vx, lx, rx, vy*2+1, my+1, ry, x, y, new_val);
		t[vx][vy] = t[vx][vy*2] + t[vx][vy*2+1];
	}
}
 
void update_x (int vx, int lx, int rx, int x, int y, int new_val) {
	if (lx != rx) {
		int mx = (lx + rx) / 2;
		if (x <= mx)
			update_x (vx*2, lx, mx, x, y, new_val);
		else
			update_x (vx*2+1, mx+1, rx, x, y, new_val);
	}
	update_y (vx, lx, rx, 1, 0, m-1, x, y, new_val);
}
// Code...